export default {
  notes: [
    {
      heading: "Introduction",
      content: "Electric charge is a fundamental property of matter..."
    }
  ],
  mcqs: [
    {
      question: "SI unit of charge is?",
      options: ["Coulomb", "Ampere", "Volt", "Ohm"],
      answer: 0
    }
  ],
  pyqs: [
 
  {
    question: "Which one of the following is not the product of transgenic experiments?",
    options: [
      "(A) Drought-resistant crops",
      "(B) Pest-resistant crop variety",
      "(C) Production of insulin by rDNA technique",
      "(D) High nutritional value in grains"
    ],
    answer: "(C) Production of insulin by rDNA technique"
  },

  {
    question: "Out of the following, select the correct match :",
    options: [
      "(A) Cotton plant - Meloidegyne incognitia",
      "(B) ELISA - Antigen antibody interaction",
      "(C) Transgenic cow milk - Human beta-lactalbumin protein",
      "(D) Corn Borer - Cry II Ab gene"
    ],
    answer: "(B) ELISA - Antigen antibody interaction"
  },

  {
    question: "GEAC stands for",
    options: [
      "(A) Genome Engineering Action Committee",
      "(B) Ground Environment Action Committee",
      "(C) Genetic Engineering Approval Committee",
      "(D) Genetic and Environment Approval Committee"
    ],
    answer: "(C) Genetic Engineering Approval Committee"
  },

  {
    question: "RNA interference (RNAi) helps in making tobacco plant resistant to nematode by",
    options: [
      "(A) Preventing translation of mRNA of nematode",
      "(B) Preventing replication of DNA of nematode",
      "(C) Preventing replication of plant DNA",
      "(D) Preventing transcription of plant DNA"
    ],
    answer: "(A) Preventing translation of mRNA of nematode"
  },

  {
    question: "The technique for early detection of disease based on antigen-antibody interaction is",
    options: [
      "(A) ELISA",
      "(B) PCR",
      "(C) RNAi",
      "(D) EST"
    ],
    answer: "(A) ELISA"
  },

  {
    question: "Which transgenic animal is used to test safety of polio vaccine?",
    options: [
      "(A) Sheep",
      "(B) Goat",
      "(C) Pig",
      "(D) Mice"
    ],
    answer: "(D) Mice"
  },

  {
    question: "The improved trait in Golden Rice is",
    options: [
      "(A) Insect resistance",
      "(B) High Vitamin-A content",
      "(C) High lysine content",
      "(D) High protein content"
    ],
    answer: "(B) High Vitamin-A content"
  },

  {
    question: "Who challenged the patent for turmeric wound healing?",
    options: [
      "(A) Dr. Venugopalan",
      "(B) Dr. R.A. Mashelkar",
      "(C) Ms. Vandana Shiva",
      "(D) Mr. Ajay Phadke"
    ],
    answer: "(B) Dr. R.A. Mashelkar"
  },

  {
    question: "Micropropagation can be achieved by",
    options: [
      "(A) Tissue culture",
      "(B) Self-pollination",
      "(C) Asexual reproduction",
      "(D) Vegetative propagation"
    ],
    answer: "(A) Tissue culture"
  },

  {
    question: "Nematode specific genes were introduced into tobacco plant using vector",
    options: [
      "(A) Agrobacterium",
      "(B) Plasmid",
      "(C) pBR322",
      "(D) Bacteriophage"
    ],
    answer: "(A) Agrobacterium"
  },



    {
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology and its Applications",
  assertion: "A patient of ADA deficiency undergoing treatment for gene therapy requires periodic infusion of genetically engineered lymphocytes.",
  reason: "Lymphocytes are immortal.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},
{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology and its Applications",
  assertion: "Patents are granted by government to an inventor.",
  reason: "Patents prevents others from commercial use of an invention.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},

{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology and its Applications",
  assertion: "In molecular diagnosis, single stranded DNA or RNA tagged with radioactive molecule is called a probe.",
  reason: "A probe always searches and hybridises with its complementary DNA in a clone of cells.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},

{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology and its Applications",
  assertion: "Indian Government has set up an organisation known as GEAC to decide the validity of GM research.",
  reason: "Genetic modification of organisms has no effect when such organisms are introduced in the ecosystem.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},
{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Biotechnology: Principles and Processes",
  assertion: "Agrobacterium tumefaciens is a pathogen of several monocot plants.",
  reason: "It is able to deliver a piece of DNA known as 'T-DNA' to transform normal plant cells into a tumor.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},

{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Strategies for Enhancement in Food Production",
  assertion: "The meristems are grown 'in vitro' to obtain virus-free plants from an infected plant.",
  reason: "If the plant is infected with a virus, the roots and the stems are free of virus.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},
{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Strategies for Enhancement in Food Production",
  assertion: "Isolated single cells can be fused to produce somatic hybrids.",
  reason: "Cells selected for somatic hybridisation have desirable characters.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},
{
  type: "assertion-reason",
  subject: "Biology/Strategies for Enhancement in Food Production",
  assertion: "To generate only a part of the plant from a cell is totipotency.",
  reason: "Suitable special nutrient media and sterile conditions are required in 'in vitro' conditions for the division of cells in explants.",
  options: [
    "(A) Both true & correct explanation",
    "(B) Both true but incorrect explanation",
    "(C) A true R false",
    "(D) A false R true",
  ],
  year: "2026",
},
  ]
};
